A Guide to the Francis Nicholson Papers, 1680-1721
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Francis Nicholson Papers, 1680-1721.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 43.4
1 volume and 83 items.
Francis Nicholson.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1943.
Alternative Form
Available on microfilm M-1554. Photocopy of "Treatise on the Flora and Fauna of Virginia" (PH/02/11) and selected transcripts (TR/21) also available.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Nicholson (1660-1728) was one of the chief founders and benefactors of the College of William and Mary, lieutenant governor of Virginia, 1690-1692, and governor, 1698-1705.
Scope and Content Information
Letters and papers of Francis Nicholson. The papers contain five main subjects: the college; Nicholson's infatuation for Lucy Burwell; Nicholson's colonial administration; addresses to the Crown; and church affairs. The feud between Nicholson and Commissary James Blair, president of the college, is apparent through all five.
The collection includes "Treatise on the Flora and Fauna of Virginia, 1680," an early partial copy of one of the first scientific accounts of Virginia's plants, insects, and mollusks, by the Rev. John Banister; a letter from Blair to Nicholson reporting Robert Boyle's bequest to the College, February 27, 1691/2; letters from John Locke to Nicholson and Blair; Blair's 1703 "Memorial Concerning my troubles and Conduct in Virginia with relacion to Governor Nicholson and the Causes of my Coming for England," which he sent Dr. Tenison, Archbishop of Canterbury; and a petition against Nicholson from members of the Council of Virginia to Queen Anne, May 20, 1703. Also, the draft of a letter from Nicholson to Henry Compton, Bishop of London, requesting that his "Accusers may be obliged to give Under their hands what they have to lay to my Charge," July 29, 1702.
Among the correspondents are Lewis Burwell, Benjamin Harrison, the Rev. Mungo Ingles, Richard Ingoldsby, the Rev. Owen Jones, Philip Ludwell, Lord Nottingham, Col. Robert Quary, Lt. John Riggs, and Lord Weymouth.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Material at the John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library
There is one collection within Special Collections, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library that relates to this collection. This is the Francis Nicholson Papers, 1695-1765.
The Francis Nicholson Papers, 1695-1765, Special Collections, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library; including correspondence to Nicholson, governor of Virginia, and papers concerning Nicholson's will.
Francis Nicholson Papers, 1695-1765. 17 items. MS 86.10
Index Terms
Persons:
Banister, John, 1650-1692.; Blair, James, 1656-1743.; Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.; Burwell, Lewis, d. 1710.; Burwell, Lucy.; Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1645-1713.; Ingles, Mungo, Reverend.; Ingoldsby, Richard, Sir, d. 1685.; Jones, Owen.; Locke, John, 1632-1704.; Ludwell, Phillip, 1672- 1727.; Nicholson, Francis, 1655-1728.; Nottingham, Daniel Finch, Earl of, 1647-1730.; Quary, Robert.; Riggs, John.; Weymouth, Lord.
Subjects:
Botany--Virginia.; Colonial administrators--Virginia.; Courtship--Virginia.; Love poetry, American--Virginia--Williamsburg.
Corporate Names:
College of William and Mary.
Geographical Names:
Virginia-- Politics and government--To 1775.
Contents List
- Partial copy of "1680 Treatise on the Flora and Fauna of Virginia." 1680 (Folder 1)
- Letter. London, [Blair] to [Nicholson], incomplete, pp. 1-4, An Account of the College Business [note: rest of letter in VMHB VII (1900) pp. 160-163.] 3 December 1691 (Folder 2)
- Letter. London, James Blair to Francis Nicholson. 27 February 1691/2 (Folder 2)
- Petition of James Blair to Sir Edward [Edmund] Andros with two accounts. 19 October 1693 (Folder 2)
- Letter. London, Benjamin Harrison, Jr. to [Nicholson], Gov. of Maryland. 1 September 1698 (Folder 2)
- Virginia, James City, [Nicholson] to Bishop of London, draft. 4 February 1698/9 (Folder 2)
- James City, Francis Nicholson to Sheriffs, Governor's order for birds for King William, endorsed. 1 March 1698/9 (Folder 2)
- Letter. James City, [Francis Nicholson] to "Your Ladyship" [Lucy Burwell], draft. 10 March 1698/9 (Folder 2)
- 5 Student Speeches (numbered separately). [1 May 1699] (Folder 2)
- Proposition by James Blair for supplying Virginia with Clergy. 6 September 1699 (Folder 3)
- Letter. London, J[ohn] Locke to [Francis Nicholson], endorsed. 10 October 1699 (Folder 3)
- Letter. London, J[ohn] Locke to James Blair, endorsed. 16 October 1699 (Folder 3)
- Letter. James Town, Francis Nicholson to the High Sheriff of New Kent County, Commands about ministers, etc. executed. 3 March 1699/1700 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Nicholson to [Micajah or Richard Perry], draft incomplete, pp. 3-6. [Winter or early spring 1699/1700] (Folder 3)
- Letter. Bishop of London to Francis Nicholson, incomplete, p. 3. [April-Aug. 1700] (Folder 3)
- Letter. Middle Plantation, James Blair to [Francis Nicholson] 2 copies of which one endorsed. 9 August 1700 (Folder 3)
- Letter. [Francis Nicholson] to Major Burwell. 14 March 1700/1 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Lewis Burwell to [Francis Nicholson]. 15 March 1700/1 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Francis Nicholson to Major Burwell. Note: all on same sheet, contemporary copies. 21 March [1700/1] (Folder 3)
- [Francis Nicholson] to Major Lewis Burwell (2 letters), and Burwell to Nicholson, copies. 14-21 March 1700/1 (Folder 3)
- Letter. [Francis Nicholson] to [Mrs. Burwell]. 24 March 1700/1 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Williamsburg, [Nicholson] to Major Dent. 18 July 1701 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Williamsburg, [Nicholson] to Major Dent. Copies. Note: 2 on same sheet. 27 August 1701 (Folder 3)
- Council and Burgesses to King. Date from C. S. P. XIX. [27 September 1701] (Folder 3)
- Letter. Whitehall, Lord Nottingham to [Francis Nicholson], copy. 7 May 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. J. Braine, Channel Daltmo[uth] Dist[rict], to Nicholson. 16 July 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. On board the H. M. S. Southampton, off Capes [of Va.] [Nicholson] to [Bishop of London], draft. 29 July 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Virginia, [Nicholson] to Lt. John Riggs. 7 August 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Bishop of London to F. Nicholson, endorsed. 7 October 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Chelsey [?] to F. [Nicholson]. 8 December 1702 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Lewis Burwell to F. [Nicholson], copies 2 on one sheet. 26 December 1702 and 6 January 1702/3 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to [Lewis Burwell], drafts of 2 letters on same sheet. 4 January 1702/3 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to [Lucy Burwell], draft. 7 January 1702/3 (Folder 4)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to Mrs. Burwell, draft. 7 January 1702/3 (Folder 4)
- Letter. House of Burgesses to Queen Anne. 10 April 1703 (Folder 5)
- Letter. Members of Council to Queen Anne, endorsed, attested copy. 20 May 1703 (Folder 5)
- Letter. New York, Lt. John Riggs to F. [Nicholson]. 15 July 1703 (Folder 5)
- Letter. Nicholson to [?], incomplete. [Summer of 1703?] (Folder 5)
- Letter. Col. Robert Quary to [Bishop of London?]. 15 October 1703 (Folder 5)
- Latin Poem to Nicholson. 5 November 1703 (Folder 5)
- Blair to [Archbishop of Canterbury], Memorial against Nicholson, with reasons for coming to England. [ca. October-November 1703] (Folder 5)
- Letter. London, Lord Weymouth to Nicholson, endorsed. 9 February 1703/4 (Folder 5)
- N. D. Copy of letter, Owen Jones to Bishop of London, with Richard Ingoldesby to Bishop of London, on same sheet. 11 February 1703/4 (Folder 5)
- Copy of the Affidavit of Stephen Fouace, clerk, relating to the Mal: Administrations of Col: Nicholson, Governor of Virginia; Sworn the 25 of April 1704. 25 April 1704 (Folder 6)
- Blair's Affidavit, endorsed copy. 25 April 1704 (Folder 6)
- Further Affidavit of James Blair, 2 copies with 1 endorsed. 1 May 1704 (Folder 6)
- Affidavit of Capt. James Moodie, endorsed copy. 1 May 1704 (Folder 6)
- An abstract of the Chief Articles of Gov. Nicholson Mal Administrations in Virginia, 3 copies. 24 May 1704 (Folder 7)
- Affidavit of James Blair, clerk endorsed copy. 7 June 1704 (Folder 7)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to Col. Custis, draft. 12 June 1704 (Folder 7)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to Madame Page, draft. 14 November 1704 (Folder 7)
- Ballad Address to defend Gov. Nicholson, this manuscript printed in London 1704. "1704" (Folder 7)
- Letter. Williamsburg, F. [Nicholson] to Rev. Guy Smith, draft. 20 January 1704/5 (Folder 7)
- Letter. Virginia, [?] to [Nicholson ??]. 20 February 1704/5 (Folder 7)
- Letter. Williamsburg, John Hall to Mr. Hyde Torway. 5 March 1704/5 (Folder 7)
- Letter. Virginia, Nicholson to [?]. 8 March 1704/5 (Folder 7)
- William and Mary College, Rev. Mongo Ingles to F. [Nicholson], 2 copies one of which is amended attested copy sent [Gov. Nott]. 8 August 1705 (Folder 7)
- Williamsburg, Minutes of meeting of Clergy of Virginia. 29 August 1705 (Folder 8)
- Williamsburg, Minutes of meeting of Clergy of Virginia re: Nicholson, with letter of Bishop of London, 29 April 1705. 29 August - 21 September 1705 (Folder 8)
- Memorandum re several faults in the Building of William and Mary College. [ca. 1703-1705] (Folder 8)
- Letter. Virginia, [Rev. Mongo Ingles ?] to Nicholson. 22 December 1705 (Folder 8)
- Rev. Mongo Ingles to Nicholson, copy attested by N., can't tell if date is when made or when attested. 7 February 1705/6 [?] (Folder 8)
- Virginia, Col. Philip Ludwell to F. Nicholson. 27 March 1717 (Folder 8)
- Memorandum to "His Excellency" on state of Virginia [not to Governor of Virginia]. [ca. summer-fall 1721] (Folder 8)
- Memorandum to go to Mr. Blair. Mentions Col. Ludwell and Lucy Ludwell. N. D. (Folder 9)
- Memorandum to Major Burwells. N. D. (Folder 9)
- Memorandum to go in the morning to Major Burwells. N. D. (Folder 9)
- Memorandum to tell Major Burwell. N. D.
- Memo (at night) re going to Major Burwell in the morning. 27 February (Folder 9)
- Memo to desire Major Burwell to send. N.D. (Folder 9)
- Letter. [Francis Nicholson] to my dear Soul [lucy Burwell]. Also [Francis Nicholson] to My dear Saint [Lucy Burwell] on same sheet. N.D. (Folder 9)
- Letter. Williamsburg, [Francis Nicholson] to My dear Dove [Lucy Burwell]. 30 December (Folder 9)
- Poem to Lucy Burwell. N.D. (Folder 9)
- Poem to Lucy Burwell. N.D. (Folder 9)
- Poem. "Virginia's Complaint Against the Plantiffs," 2 copies. N.D.
- Ballad. "The Barter." N.D. (Folder 9)
- Poem. "The Rackett." N.D. (Folder 9)